but I want to tell you a story now and
it has these characters in it and so
this is a very important story and it's
called the Enuma Elish and it's the
Mesopotamian creation myth and it's
important for a bunch of reasons first
of all it's the oldest written story we
know of but it's also a Middle Eastern
story and the whole all the Abrahamic
religions emerged out of the Middle East
and so it's a foundational story it's a
story that sits at the bottom of our
culture now it has it has similarities
to the creation story in Genesis whether
the creation story in Genesis was
derived from it or whether there was a
whole variety of similar stories
floating around in the Middle East and
at the same time that were variants of a
theme we don't really know but it
doesn't read I don't think it really
matters we don't know how old the story
is we know how old it is in its written
form it's it's it's thousands of years
old in its written form maybe it's ten
thousand years old it's written form but
probably not it's probably more like
five thousand years old but the thing is
is that a 5,000 year old story is a lot
that's written is way older than 5,000
years like we're used to being in an
environment where there's a million
stories you know because we have books
and movies and all of these things but
you know in its slower moving and more
archaic cultures especially ones that
are just just have an oral tradition
it's not like there's a million stories
there's like 20 canonical stories and
god only knows how old they are there
was evidence linguistic evidence I just
saw a study on this last week someone
sent it to me showing that some of the
fairy tales that the Grimm brothers
gathered might be 10,000 years old and
that doesn't surprise me because the
kind of depth that's in a good fairy
tale is is so the depth is so the
profundity is so deep that
no way that someone could just conjured
it up you know 100 years ago it's
there's layers and layers and layers of
meaning and they're basically archetypal
and religious in significance and Hansel
and Gretel story is a good example of
that and Sleeping Beauty is a good
example about - a lot of the canonical
fairy tales are they're very very
powerful they pack a lot of meaning into
a very short into a very limited amount
of time so so it was great that this was
unearthed and it was only unearthed in
the late 1800s so we haven't known about
this story you know for a long long time
and so it's it was a tremendously
exciting discovery on the part of the
people who who dug it up so I'm going to
tell you the story so the primary
character in this story is a like a
dragon mother named time at and time at
you could think about her as half the
dragon of chaos and half the destructive
creative feminine so she you could think
about her as what's sort of on the
border between what's a known known and
an unknown in unknown and she's
construed as the mother of all things
now the mother of all things is like
what was revealed when the towers came
down it's this tremendously complex
background multi-level system of
operations that's always going on that
that identifiable singular things emerge
from now the Mesopotamians wouldn't have
said that because what they said was
this story because that's the form in
which their knowledge had it had
developed to the point where they could
tell a story about instead of maybe
acting it out or dreaming about it in
some sense you know but they couldn't
articulate it we can barely articulate
it now so there's time out she's viewed
as the mother of all things and she has
a husband named AB sue who's her concert
very little is said about AB sue in this
particular story and I think the reason
for that although I'm not sure of this
is that the Mesopotamian civilization
was knew enough as a technological state
let's say because it made cities as a
technological state that the meant that
myths of humanity hadn't figure out how
to encapsulate the nature of the of a
technological dominance art there was a
sense that it existed but there wasn't a
sense of it has a care of differentiated
character that was capable of doing all
sorts of different things I think that
didn't emerge until Egypt although I'm
not certain that but that's how it looks
to me so absolute is her husband now the
way the Mesopotamians thought of the
world and this is the same way that the
people who wrote Genesis thought of the
world they thought of that the world was
a disc you know what what the world's
like when you go outside and you stand
in a field it's a flat field you look at
the world it's pretty obvious what it is
it's a big disc of Earth and then
there's a dome on top of it and in the
dome art of the Sun and the moon and the
stars and then you might ask well what's
underneath earth and the answer for the
Mesopotamians was fresh water first and
then salt water how did you know that
well if you drill down then up the fresh
water would come so obviously there was
fresh water down there and then if you
went to the edge of your territory it's
like well there's the salt water so the
earth was you know let the earth roughly
speaking was a disk of matter resting on
a disk of fresh water resting on a disk
of salt water an absolute time at were
the fresh and saltwater respect okay and
there now the Mesopotamians thought that
the way that the that absolute time that
gave birth to everything was that they
join together in sexual union like the
yin in the egg and it's very much like
that exact and that it was out of their
union that the the elemental gods
emerged and I think you can think of the
elemental gods as their their their
forces of nature and they're viewed
through their not personified because to
personify something means that you see
it as an objective phenomena and then
attribute human characteristics to it
and that isn't how people work
what happens is we
perceive human characteristics and then
only with terrible effort do we extract
out the objective reality from that so
we D personalize things when we become
scientific but we just naturally see
them as characters and you can see this
when you read books to kids you know
like everything's a person train is a
person and a car as a person the moon is
a person and the Sun is a person and you
know you read stories to children that
have that as a presupposition doesn't
bother you at all you know you can just
fall right into it with no problem you
know and in the animations you see the
Sun in the sky smiling and bouncing
along and it doesn't bother you you know
it's no problem to look at the world
that way and there's some utility in
looking at the world in that way as
we'll discover so anyways and I think
part of the reason that we view things
that way oh yeah that was the other
thing I wanted to tell you about our
perceptual systems is that we we do have
a social cognitive platform intellectual
platform which means that our primary
categories the primary categories of our
mind do seem to be social so you could
say that the reason our mind evolved or
no what you could say that the
fundamental selecting pressures on our
on our mind ensured that the the primary
substructure of our cognitive ability
was modules that could understand social
behavior men can understand women women
could understand men men and women could
understand children children men and
women could understand the social world
and that's and that's that's what we're
specialized for and then it was only
after those systems developed hyper
developed probably under the under the
force of sexual selection that they
became able to separate themselves to
some degree from that underlying social
cognitive structure and start to see the
world in ways that were personified so
but what that means is that our natural
categories are still and anthropomorphic
and dramatic it actually turns out they
work so absolute time now nature and
culture is a perfectly reasonable way of
thinking about them now they would say
well
it's the interplay between nature and
culture that gives rise to the
primordial forces of nature
now those forces of nature would be to
some degree external like a storm or
like fire but they would be sucked to
some degree internal - like like the
fire of passion right and the and the
storm of sorrow because those are
natural forces as well and one of the
things that the ancients knew was that
man was created to serve the gods and of
course modern people think of that as a
superstition but that's because they
don't really understand how archaic
people thought archaic people thought
like Freud thought it's like yeah yeah
you have an ego fine you know as long as
you're in a box within a bunch of other
boxes the eagle runs things but as soon
as we put you somewhere where those
boxes are gone it's the underlying
forces of nature that run you hunger
thirst
you know aggression sexuality and all
those things that are impersonal because
of course you have them and you have
them and so does everyone else so
they're impersonal and transcendent and
they're also eternal and so when the
archaic people said and they usually
said this with sorrow that man was
destined to serve the gods that's what
they meant they meant that we were the
playthings of these unbelievably
powerful primordial forces that
manifested themselves within our lives
and determined our destinies and in an
in fact a Mesopotamian said that
specifically about the Elder Gods they
said they were they were part of that
which determined human destiny
Marduk who we'll talk about in a while
was given the tablet of destinies
because when he was when he asked to
become top god he said well if I'm going
to be taught to determine the destinies
and well we'll get to that so you kind
of got to know what these what these
archaic gods work and they were
personalities you know when you could
say well yeah yeah maybe it's a mistake
to attribute the qualities of
personality to a storm although it
depends on what you think a storm is
like a modern person would think of a
storm as an objective event that you
have subjective reactions
- and our CAD person would more likely
think of the storm as the subjective
consequences of the storm plus the storm
all at once they would make that
separation so it's a lot easier to
personify something under those
conditions or to not to personify it but
- but to stay within the realm of
conceptualization that makes it a
personified force so the storm god is
something that you know that can instill
terror into your heart it's like well
you know yeah fair enough you know
alright so anyways absolute timeout they
give rise to these primordial gods and
I'm going to think about them as forces
of nature and I think that's a
reasonable representation for a variety
of reasons they're like the Titans
alright so they give rise to these gods
and the gods are their children and they
run about making all sorts of racket
they're making rocket and they're doing
this and they're doing that they're
building things and they're messing
about with things and they're they're
noisily engaged in their interactions
with one another and they're having
children and they're fighting about sex
and they're just making racket like mad
and then they do something stupid and so
they're annoying time out as they make
all this racket she's sort of slumbering
down there in the depths leaving them be
but they make all this racket and they
annoy her it's like it's the
environmentalist myth by the way it's
exactly the same idea so you know human
beings were kind of dopey we're running
around gratifying our fundamental needs
and making racket and destroying things
and if we're not careful Mother Nature
will come flooding back and like wipe us
out it's like yeah that's happened in
the past it could happen but it's an
archetypal it's an archetypal idea it's
a mythological idea so fine they're
making racket and time outs leaving the
bee but then they get arrogant I would
say or careless and they they kill opsin
and they make their dwelling place on
his corpse now that's a that is a
brilliant brilliant symbolic idea
because what it means it means a bunch
of things but one of the things it means
is that insofar as the gods are because
they're masculine they're part of the
represent
of the dominants hearty and human
interactions within it that the idea
that that that that's all existing on
the corpse of ab su is something like
the idea that all of the natural forces
that are embodied within human beings
and driving them are resting on a sub
structure of dead culture and everyone
knows that because everyone says
especially modern people they look back
at their culture and they think all that
things dead you know and we can rest
comfortably on it's dead surface well
that's not right because if it's dead
well if it's dead logically speaking
it's not alive than if it's not alive it
can't adapt if it doesn't adapt then it
falls behind and gets full of errors and
it gets corrupt it starts to fall apart
and if it gets corrupted full of errors
and falls apart enough then chaos comes
back that's exactly what happens in the
Mesopotamian myth so they kill apps ooh
and they keep making racket and time at
wakes up one day and she thinks oh
they're noisy I don't like them that
much and now they've gone and done in my
husband which is order so I'm going to
wake them out so the guards get wind of
this and they're not very happy about it
you know because after all they're gone
but she is the God goddess / dragon that
gave them all life and the probability
that they'll prevail in a battle against
that which gave them form is very very
low so they're pretty damn terrified so
meanwhile time at is generating her army
and she generates quite an army and that
Mesopotamians lists out what she does
she she first of all picks for her
concert a new character named King mu
and King o is like the king of the demon
monsters so her old husband was absolute
maybe he was order and her new husband
is like he's not someone that you want
to have around at all and so he's
basically put at the hand of this
phalanx of terrible monsters and she
generates like scorpion monsters and
crocodile monsters and all sorts of
things in her army so that she can go
wipe out these these gods and so well
this is happening
the gods gathered themselves together
and they decide that they'll elected
champion from within their ranks to go
out and fight with time app and so they
do that they send one God out he comes
back with his tail between his legs
roughly speaking all right don't let his
encounter with chaos and then they send
another God out the same thing happens
and they send another God out the same
thing happens and it's getting pretty
damn hopeless because they're sending
out their best men against chaos and
them and the mother of all things and
they're getting scuttled all the time
while this was happening they continue
to produce new generations of gods and
at one point this new god emerges as a
young person I presume um but he's
there's some things that are different
than about him than any other thing
that's being produced so far and one of
the things that's different is he's
quite tall and powerful so you know
that's not necessarily so radical but he
has eyes all the way around his head and
when he speaks he can speak darkness
into being and he can speak light into
being so so things obey the commands of
his words so he's a master of language
he can see everywhere and he's a master
of language okay and so the gods are
checking him out what they think well
you know he's he's quite something maybe
we can get him to go after time at so
they all go to him in this in this
little group and they say look Marduk
because that's his name um you know
we've been checking you out and you're
looking pretty impressive and so we've
got a proposition for you how about if
you go fight time out and Marduk who's
not only all-seeing and and very capable
with language is no fool and he says
yeah yeah yeah I get what you want but
here's the deal you get everybody
together first and I'll go fight your
monster but you're going to have a
Congress and at that Congress you're
going to elect me king of the gods and
then I'll go fight time app and so of
course the other gods aren't very happy
about this but they go off and they have
a Congress and they invite mark to it
and they talk about it and they realize
they don't really have any other choice
so they decide that they're going to
elect Marduk to the top of the hierarchy
of gods now that's such a smart idea so
if you think for example you can think
of a hero and then you can think if you
took ten heroes and add
which them out of that you get a god
right
so it'd be ten heroes you get a meta
here out of that and that would be a god
and then maybe you do that to ten sets
of ten heroes and you get ten meta
heroes and then you take all those meta
heroes and you figure out what's the
same about them and you abstract that
out and then you get the hero of Heroes
of Heroes and that's the archetype
that's the archetype it's a process of
distillation it's like who's the most
interesting possible the most
interesting and capable possible person
well that would be this person this is
the most memorable possible person well
we don't know who that is but this is
how we figure it out now I could say
well I admire something about you and I
admire something about you I can notice
that as a phenomenological fact you seem
very capable in a certain way and you
know you have this attribute and then I
might say well if I was going to sort
out an ideal for myself to follow then I
take the good parts of all of you and I
put that into one thing and then I would
make that my ideal well that's the
origin of the idea of the savior of the
Messiah
that's an emergent idea it emerges when
people notice that the hero is that the
hero is part of the force that makes
order out of chaos or sometimes the
reverse when when order has become too
rigid it can also decompose order bring
a little necessary chaos into it
rejuvenate the whole structure so
anyways so Marduk he gets elected King
now you might think about how would this
happen historically speaking well here's
an interesting way of thinking about it
so imagine a landscape that consists of
tribes okay
and then on top of them imagine a
landscape of the imagination okay so
each member of each tribal group lives
in their imagined world and that
imagined world is full of dandies and
natural forces of various kinds that
they're following but then you can
imagine that as the tribes battle it out
and organize themselves the figures of
the imagination do exactly the same
thing so as the people are battling the
gods in heaven are battling which is
also very common mythology and as the
human beings
I beat themselves into a functional
group their world conceptions do the
same thing and so over time you move
from polytheism roughly speaking to
monotheism as the the as all these
tribes communicate with one another in
language and in combat and sort out just
exactly what should be sovereign what
should be powerful what should be
dominant right it's a major it's a major
issue and it's partly practical it's
partly conceptual so if this is
reflected in the Mesopotamian creation
myth the gods assemble themselves and
they look among them and they think okay
well someone here is has the
characteristics that should should be
the central element of the top deity
which is like the ultimate value okay
while the Mesopotamians chose wisely
vision and language those are you most
the most potent weapons you have against
chaos because you if you pay attention
you can see chaos when it first emerges
and then if you are a master of language
you can encapsulate it and articulate it
very rapidly and you can communicate
that to other peoples it's like now this
you you just cannot overestimate how
radical an idea that is it's a
staggeringly radical idea that that's
the set of attributes that should be at
the top the Mesopotamians are trying to
figure out what should be sovereign what
should be above everything else well you
might say a person it's like yeah yeah
no the person embodies sovereignty
sovereignty itself is something else
so when Fran's de Waal for example he
was watching chimpanzees hash it out for
dominance in in in the zoo and I think
it's in Holland Arnhem
I think anyways it's a zoo that has a
lot of chimpanzees in it he spent a lot
of time watching them and you know one
idea about the doorman and chimp is that
he's just biggest meanest like most
tyrannical chimp it's sort of the
strongman theory of chimp leadership but
what do all observed was that well that
was sort of true in that the strongest
and
meanest chimpanzee could obtain
dominance but the problem with him is if
he was really like selfish and cruel was
that he didn't have any friends
now chimps have friends and they spend a
lot of time with them and they groom
each other and they protect each other
in fights and like you can be the
ugliest meanest chimp around but if
there's two chimps that are
three-quarters your strength coming out
at you it's like you you lose now so
that means two chimps that are capable
of enough civilization to bind
themselves in to a dyad that is that has
mutual obligations across time is way
stronger than one ship who doesn't and
so what that means is that strength and
viciousness you know there will be times
when that can emerge as the dominant
power but it's very very unstable and
and everyone's motivated to bring it
down as fast as possible and the best
way to bring it down is with a coalition
and so partly what that indicates is
that it's actually the chimp who's the
best at making coalition's that's most
likely to become sovereign so that and
that's actually what happens with the
chimps is that the dictator chimp is
very unstable in in the one story I
rented of Arnhem at the armed zoo he
rose to the top though you know bad bad
guy that gangster guy and two chimps
went after me torn to pieces they tore
off his testicles yeah and you know it
agitated the hell out of the rest of the
troop and it was looking like a bloody
revolution you know it was really really
stressful for the troop but but what it
indicates and it's so interesting is
that the idea that in a in a dominance
hierarchy what's most dominant is a
power that there's no evidence
whatsoever that that's true and in fact
I was talking to what I have a partner
in a business that I have who was a
student of mine at Harvard he is a very
very smart person and I was talking to
him about dominance hierarchies and he
said something very that I found very
upsetting on a variety of levels he said
it's not a dominance herky if you can't
put a dog collar on the person one level
below you which is pretty bloody blunt
statement but when he's prone to that
sort of thing but what he meant is that
it's possible that the idea that the
term dominance higher
is not the right term to be applying to
these sorts of social structures because
what it implies is that what keeps the
structure in place is power you know and
that's the sort of claim that people
like Foucault make it's all about power
it's like the thing is it's not all
about power it's not all about power
it's not all about power among animals
so with power with chimps if that's all
you've got is power you're going to get
wiped out you have to so what do all
found was that the chimps who were able
to establish stable patterns of
leadership were quite congenial they had
a lot of allies so they engaged in
mutual grooming and a lot of social
interaction and they were very
positively predisposed to the females in
the troop so that's pretty interesting
you know because we don't know what
constitutes valid sovereignty but even
in animals it doesn't seem to be power
so and then you know you look at wolf
pack's and that sort of thing and you
know if two wolves go at it for
dominance one wolf for back off and roll
over and show his throat and you know
like Stalin wolf would just tear out his
throat but you know um
Churchill wolf let's say would say well
yeah you're kind of useless but we might
need you around later so why don't you
get up and you know we'll let bygones be
bygones and that's what wolves do you
know and and unsurprisingly because what
are you going to do kill everyone in
your troop well that doesn't seem like a
very effective strategy either for
mating or for survival so the
Mesopotamians are trying to work out
practically who's going to be sovereign
and at the same time conceptually what
is the proper basis for sovereignty
which is it's really the ultimate
question in some sense so anyway so they
elect marnik and the Martok's got all
these eyes and he can speak and so he
thinks all right it says if I win I'm
going to get the tablet of destinies and
then I'm talking on and they say yeah
yeah whatever if you win no problem so
she goes out to fight timeout and he
takes a sword and he and he takes a net
and they meet on the battlefield and he
encapsulate stye map in
which i think is a brilliant brilliant
metaphor again because chaos is
amorphous and unformed right and if you
want to conquer it you have to
encapsulate it within a net a network
you have to you have to make it into
something rather than something
amorphous you know and so look maybe a
client comes to me and they say oh I've
been having these terrible symptoms on
my heart races and I'm my breath I can't
catch my breath and I think I'm going to
die and I think maybe I'm having a heart
attack and I'm always at the hospital
and they tell me that there's nothing
wrong with me and but I have like I'm
I'm afraid all the time and I'm starting
not to go out and I say oh you have a
graph obeah lots of people have that
you're not the only person like that in
the world not only that it has a name we
know what to do about it and there's a
treatment course and they go and the
reason for that is that the unknown
unknown has just been turned into a
known unknown and that's a massive
improvement and so the person who
conceptualizes the anomalous situation
fastest is in fact the leader that's the
definition of leadership it's like we
don't know what's going on this is
what's going on and what and when you
say this is what's going on you also
simultaneously say here's a million
other things that could have been going
on that aren't so it's a process of
radical simplification and it lowers the
stress levels immediately anyway so time
that goes and or martica as he gets her
in a net and then he splits her in half
and he makes heaven out of one half and
the earth other the other for the human
beings and and he goes back to and he
defeats Keo and all the monsters and
then he goes back to tell the other gods
and they're pretty happy about this and
king who had the tablet of destinies but
mardik took that from him and now he has
it so he gets to determine destiny and
he makes human beings out of Kings blood
which is quite an interesting little
twist to the story and he makes them to
serve the gods and so so that's that
soul so the idea is that the hero who
can see and can communicate is also the
hero who separates out
the elements of existence so that it
becomes a habitable place and that
humans should serve that serve Marduk we
have to serve something well you're
going to serve a natural force of some
sort in the all anger you can be all
lust it can be all love or you can be
all hunger or you going to represent
some integrated ah some some balance
that integrated emergent property of
that that's also socially constructed
you know so that you're a balance of
natural forces and you're a civilized
person and that's some sort of essence
and that's what you're going to strive
for well that's Martin so you're
supposed to be a good Marduk now
Margaret is immortal now the only person
who was identified with Marduk in the
Mesopotamian realm was the Emperor now
they lived in a walled city and so what
the Emperor
the reason the Emperor was sovereign was
because he was supposed to be the
embodiment of mark on earth which meant
that his job was to transform chaos into
order
whenever chaos threatened he was
supposed to transform it back into order
so this is what the Mesopotamians did at
the New Year's celebration when the Year
is rejuvenated right the old year dies
of course we know that because we still
do it and the new year is this new baby
it's a time of new beginnings
so the Mesopotamians would take the
emperor out of the city and they'd strip
him of all his emperor clothes and then
they'd make him recite all the ways
during the last year that he'd been a
bad Marduk like he hadn't kept he hadn't
been encountering chaos properly and
hadn't been keeping order properly so he
had to confess all of his inadequacies
then the priest would whack him with a
glove as a you know as a ritual
punishment and then they take all the
statues out of the old gods out of the
city and then they re read the battle
between Marduk and Tiamat and then the
Emperor was Martic and he would win and
then he would have sex with a ritual
prostitute which was that this is a much
tougher concept but it's it's a way of
symbolizing the fact that if the
creative force encounters the positive
element of the feminine it's like the
prince in Sleeping Beauty
getting Sleeping Beauty from the grasp
of the evil queen who turns into the
dragon it's exact because it's weird
right you've seen that and you
understand it right Sleeping Beauty is
all in the tower she's covered by a
she's hemmed in by a huge fields of
thorns the Evil Queen is trying to stop
the fresh from getting to her she turns
into a dragon which makes absolutely no
sense but everyone follows it and then
he has to fight his way through that to
get to the to the main it's the same
idea in a different context and then
order productive order being
reestablished everybody goes back into
the kingdom and it's renewed for the
next year and that's the idea behind
Mesopotamian sovereignty and it's bloody
brilliant because it's an abscess it's
it's it's the beginnings of law in some
sense it's it's the idea that to be to
be proper even if you're a despot even
if you're the king there's a sacred
pattern of behavior that you must adhere
to which is the consequence of a
congress of the gods deciding what the
most effective mode of being is it's
staggeringly brilliant and and it took
that story we just have no idea how long
that story took to emerge I would say
it's it's the consequence of the full
course of human evolutionary history
like there are elements in it that are
as old as mammals and maybe older than
that you know if you think about those
patterns being embedded in behavior long
before they were abstracted out into
representations it's unbelievably
archaic and ancient and so you have time
at the Great Mother you have absolute
the Great Father you have Marduk the
archetypal son you have King Oh who's
the negative element of Marduk right and
you have the drama of all those
characters interacting across time and
that's that's the myth alone that's the
mythological representation of reality
and time at to tie it into the neural
psychology that we talked about you know
we talked about anomaly right and how
anomaly you have a box that you're in it
that is your world but that box doesn't
contain everything in the world there's
a lot of things that aren't in it and
sometimes they poke their head in like a
and then that's disruptive and what do
you do well you have to you have to
voluntarily encounter this name and
either defeat it or make something
valuable of you know you can cower and
hide but all that generally means the
state grows and grows until there's
hardly any you in the box and there's
all snakes and that's actually the best
of Damien's story it's like if the Elder
Gods weren't so careless and had been
paying attention and hadn't killed
absolute time that would have stayed
asleep the whole time so mom so that's
the that's the level of isomorphism so
what's what's fascinating but I think
inevitable is that the mythology
reflects the physiology but how could it
not the physiology produced the
mythology like of course that's going to
be the case it shouldn't be a surprise
it should be it should be it should be
the reverse should be a surprise it's
like there's no relationship between
these these old stories in the way that
human beings are structured it's like
well no no that's a dumb idea so
well that's the mesopotamian creation
myth and it's it's a killer it's it's a
it's a staggering story and you know it
still sits whether we know it or not
it's it's at the very base of our
culture it's absolute that story and if
we kill it
which we will or have been then then
look out you know we know the story from
so long ago if you let your culture die
and act carelessly towards it all hell
will break loose and it's no joke so so
here we are trying to revivify it it's
pretty weird that these things happen to
be real but then if you think about it
well how could it be otherwise
you know I mean you think all these
people who live before us for the tens
of millions of years that you know we've
had our FEGLI human pre pre dissenters
were stupid they weren't and they
weren't ignorant and they weren't
superstitious or any of those things
they were they were they were tough
enough so that we're here